Donald Holden Papers
Donald Holden Papers
1962-2006
Holden, Donald, 1931-
7 linear ft.
Holden's writings (articles, books) and artwork (drawings of nude human figure in various media, watercolor landscapes); binders containing a catalog of Holden's watercolors and slides of his work in public collections; assortment of exhibition catalogs and articles about the painter.
150124
Biographical History
American artist, art educator. Published art instruction books under pseudonym, Wendon Blake.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Blake, Wendon.; Holden, Donald.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art -- Study and teaching.; Figure drawing.; Human figure in art.; Nude in art.; Painters -- United States; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Books.; Drawings (visual works); Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Writings
  - Articles (photocopies), 1964-1994; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Books (by Donald Holden)
    - Art Career Guide, 1st-4th editions (Box 1)
    - Whistler Landscapes and Seascapes (hardbound) (Box 1)
    - Whistler Landscapes and Seascapes (paperback) (Box 1)
  - Books (by Wendon Blake)
    - The Acrylic Painting Book (Box 1)
    - The Artist's Guide to Using Color (Box 1)
    - The Artists Painting Library
      - Acrylic Painting (Box 2)
      - Children's Portraits in Oil (Box 2)
      - Color in Acrylic (Box 2)
      - Color in Oil (Box 2)
      - Color in Watercolor (Box 2)
      - Figure Drawing (Box 2)
      - Figures in Oil (Box 2)
      - Landscape Drawing (Box 2)
      - Landscapes in Acrylic (Box 2)
      - Landscapes in Oil (Box 2)
      - Landscapes in Watercolor (Box 2)
      - Oil Painting (Box 2)
      - Portrait Drawing (Box 2)
      - Portraits in Oil (Box 2)
      - Seascapes in Acrylic (Box 2)
      - Seascapes in Oil (Box 2)
      - Seascapes in Watercolor (Box 2)
      - Starting to Draw (Box 2)
      - Watercolor Painting (Box 2)
    - Acrylic Watercolor Painting (Box 1)
    - The Color Book (Box 1)
    - The Complete Acrylic Painting Book (Box 1)
    - The Complete Guide to Acrylic Painting (Box 1)
    - Complete Guide to Landscape Painting in Oil (Box 1)
    - The Complete Oil Painting Book (Box 1)
    - The Complete Painting Course (Box 1)
    - The Complete Watercolor Book (Box 2)
    - Creative Color: a Practical Guide for Oil Painters (Box 2)
    - Creative Color for the Oil Painter (Box 2)
    - The Drawing Book (Box 2)
    - Farbe in der aquarellmalerei (Box 2)
    - Getting Started in Drawing (Box 2)
    - Landschaften in Öl (Box 2)
    - Landscape Painting in Oil (Box 2)
    - The Oil Painting Book (Box 2)
    - Painting in Alkyd (hardbound) (Box 2)
    - Painting in Alkyd (paperback) (Box 2)
    - The Portrait and Figure Painting Book (Box 2)
    - The Watercolor Painting Book (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles about, 1987; 1989 (Box 3)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1990-1994; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Holding institutions of original work (Box 3)
- Artwork
  - Catalog of watercolors, 8 binders (Box 4)
  - Slides of watercolors in public collections (Box 4)
  - Drawings (by date)
    - "Seated Nude" - pencil 10 x 6 1/2, 1962 (Oversize 1)
    - "Nude Back" - carbon 7 1/2 x 11, 1964 (Oversize 1)
    - "Reclining Nude" - pencil 7 x 10 3/4, 1965 (Oversize 1)
    - "Standing Nude" - White Magna on paper toned with oil wash 11 1/2 x 7 1/2, 1966 (Oversize 1)
    - "Standing Nude" - White Magna on paper toned with oil wash 11 1/2 x 7 1/2, 1967 (Oversize 1)
    - "Seated Nude" - pencil 10 x 12, 1968 (Oversize 1)
    - "Nude Back" - brown chalk 9 1/2 x 14, 1969 (Oversize 1)
    - "Seated Nude" - Prismacolor pencil 9 x 12, 1970 (Oversize 1)
    - "Standing Nude" - charcoal and chalk 9 x 12, 1971 (Oversize 1)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor pencil and wash 6 1/2 x 10 3/4, 1972 (Oversize 1)
    - "Standing Nude" - White Magna on paper toned with oil wash 11 1/2 x 8, 1974 (Oversize 1)
    - "Reclining Nude" - gray chalk on black paper 9 x 11, 1974 (Oversize 1)
    - "Reclining Nude" - Prismacolor pencil and wash 6 x 9 1/2, 1983 (Oversize 1)
    - "Seated Nude" - Prismacolor pencil 9 x 11 1/2, 1984 (Oversize 1)
    - "Reclining Nude" - Prismacolor pencil 8 1/2 x 14 1/2, 1985 (Oversize 1)
    - "Torso" - Prismacolor pencil 8 1/2 x 12, 1986 (Oversize 1)
    - "Torso" - Prismacolor pencil 12 1/2 x 8 1/2, 1987 (Oversize 1)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor pencil 11 x 10, 1988 (Oversize 2)
    - "Standing Nude" - Prismacolor pencil 14 1/2 x 10 1/2, 1989 (Oversize 2)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor crayon 8 1/2 x 10 1/2, 1991 (Oversize 2)
    - "Kneeling Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 8 1/2 x 10 1/2, 1992 (Oversize 2)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor pencil 7 1/4 x 11, 1992 (Oversize 2)
    - "Seated Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 11 1/2 x 8, 1993 (Oversize 2)
    - "Crouching Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 10 1/2 x 8 1/2, 1994 (Oversize 2)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor crayon 8 1/4 x 11 1/2, 1994 (Oversize 2)
    - "Crouching Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 9 3/4 x 12 3/4, 1995 (Oversize 2)
    - "Reclining Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 8 x 12, 1996 (Oversize 2)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor crayon 10 x 14, 1997 (Oversize 2)
    - "Reclining Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 9 1/2 x 14, 1998 (Oversize 4)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor crayon 10 x 14, 1999 (Oversize 4)
    - "Reclining Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 10 x 14, 2000 (Oversize 4)
    - "Reclining Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 9 3/4 x 14, 2001 (Oversize 4)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor crayon 10 x 14, 2002 (Oversize 4)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor crayon 10 x 14, 2003 (Oversize 4)
    - "Reclining Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 10 x 14, 2004 (Oversize 4)
    - "Nude Back" - Prismacolor crayon 10 x 14, 2005 (Oversize 4)
    - "Seated Nude" - Prismacolor crayon 10 x 14, 2006 (Oversize 4)
  - Watercolors (by date)
    - "November Light I" 7 1/2 x 10 3/4, 1987 (Oversize 2)
    - "Tidepool III" 71/4 x 10 3/4, 1987 (Oversize 2)
    - "Grand Tetons Storm I" 9 x 13, 1989 (Oversize 2)
    - "Red Cloud III" 7 1/4 x 10 3/4, 1989 (Oversize 2)
    - "Mendocino Moonlight I" 7 1/4 x 10 3/4, 1990 (Oversize 2)
    - "Yellowstone Fire XIII" 13 x 9, 1990 (Oversize 2)
    - "After the Rain II" 7 1/4 x 10 3/4, 1991 (Oversize 3)
    - "Monhegan Morning I" 13 x 9, 1992 (Oversize 3)
    - "Monhegan Surf VI" 7 1/4 x 10 3/4, 1992 (Oversize 3)
    - "Sunset at Casper I" 7 1/4 x 10 3/4, 1993 (Oversize 3)
    - "Yellowstone Fire XXXI" 7 1/4 x 10 3/4, 1993 (Oversize 3)
    - "Lake Powell III" 7 1/4 x 10 3/4, 1994 (Oversize 3)
    - "Hudson Moonlight II" 8 3/4 x 12, 1995 (Oversize 3)
    - "Dawn at Longcol I" 7 1/2 x 11, 1996 (Oversize 3)
    - "Squeaker Cove I" 8 1/2 x 12, 1996 (Oversize 3)
    - "Garson II" 8 1/2 x 12, 1997 (Oversize 3)
    - "Wooded Shore XVII" 8 1/2 x 12, 1997 (Oversize 3)
    - "Dusk at Gull Pond X" 8 1/2 x 12, 1998 (Oversize 3)
    - "Dusk in Brittany III" 7 1/2 x 11 1/4, 1999 (Oversize 3)
    - "Thomaston II" 8 3/4 x 12 1/4, 2000 (Oversize 3)
    - "Forest Fire XIV" 9 x 12, 2001 (Oversize 3)
    - "Monhegan Harbor IX" 8 3/4 x 12 1/4, 2002 (Oversize 3)
    - "Adirondack Moonlight VI" 8 1/2 x 12, 2003 (Oversize 4)
    - "Dusk at Deertrack VII" 8 3/4 x 12 1/4, 2004 (Oversize 4)
    - "Breton Coast II" 9 x 12, 2005 (Oversize 4)
    - "Dusk at Lake Powell XV" 8 1/2 x 12, 2006 (Oversize 4)